Um,
hands up those who've seen or read
anything about uh anthropic versus
Department of War.
Half about half.
Wow. Okay. Um
well I'll just suggest that if you
haven't uh if you haven't looked at the
news recently
um I'll give you a quick update.
Uh so Anthropic
which produces Claude and
various other AI systems uh had has had
a contract for several months with the
let's call it the department of defense
uh so that DoD uses Claude in various
operations and there was a clause in the
contract
that said uh Claude cannot be used for
mass surveillance of American citizens.
and cannot be used in fully autonomous
weapons.
Um, and so that that was in the contract
for a long time. And then last week uh
the secretary of defense uh Hegsith
announced that if Anthropic did not
remove those restrictions, in other
words, they wanted to be allowed to use
Claude for mass surveillance of American
citizens and fully autonomous weapons.
Uh so if Anthropic didn't remove those
restrictions
uh they would
uh cancel the contract
and
um
uh designate anthropic as a supply chain
risk uh which is like some Chinese and
Russian companies uh have been
designated because they are a supply
chain risk uh and use a defense
production act to um to then you to to
be able to override the contract and use
claude in military operations without
any restrictions. So simultaneously
saying anthropic is so unsafe that it
cannot be used in any military
application or by anyone who has a
contract with the US government and so
on. So more or less trying to destroy
the company. Uh so simultaneously it's a
supply chain risk and we're going to use
it in in every military operation uh in
the US. So uh so that was the threat and
then uh Thursday night Dario Amade uh
made a post saying we're not we're not
giving in. Uh these restrictions are
both scientifically, legally, and
morally valid. And um so uh the deadline
was 5:00 p. p.m. Eastern time on Friday.
501 Hegsth said, "Okay, you're out." Uh
Trump announced that Anthropic could no
longer have any contracts with any
entity that had any contracts with the
US government, which is sort of most of
the United States. Um and uh
and then uh OpenAI announced that it was
replacing Anthropic
uh in this contract.
Um
and initially open AAI
uh Sam Wman said
you know we have this contract and the
defend the DoD can use uh OpenAI
products for any legal purpose
and uh but reiterated their opposition
to mass surveillance and fully
autonomous weapons. And then uh and then
I think this morning OpenAI announced
that they they had in their contract an
exclusion for those things. So they have
essentially the same contract as far as
I can tell as Anthropic had
which led to Anthropic being designated
as a supply chain risk but now an OpenAI
has replaced them with the same
restrictions.
Um so there we are. The story continues.
Um I think millions of people are now
defecting from open AI to anthropic uh
as a result.
And um so this uh last week I ran the
international association for safe and
ethical AI conference in Paris with 1300
people or so and uh and this happened
this is all going on during the
conference and so there's a lot of
ferment among the members of the
association
uh for you know what what could we do
about it um so I'd be interested if
anyone has any suggestions questions.
Okay, think about it. If you have any
ideas, uh you can let me know by email
or or any other way. Okay. So,
from the sublime, no, from the
ridiculous to the sublime, from uh
nonsense going on in the real world to
the beauty of probability theory.
Um so today's lecture is going to be uh
pretty much just about probability
theory and the notation and and the
mathematical laws of probability and and
some of the basic mathematical
operations. And then on Thursday we'll
talk about
a method of
representing
large and complex probability models in
a very natural way. Um
and representation actually is something
that we haven't really studied yet in
this uh so far. Um, and partly that's
because some of the material got changed
around and that was because I was away
and Dan was here. Um, but representation
is one of the most important concepts
both in the history of philosophy and
mathematics as well as AI. So what
representation means is that you have a
a formal language syntax and semantics
for expressing information
and then uh on that basis you can derive
algorithms that manipulate the syntax
right that operate on the representation
and those algorithms produce semantic
consequences meaning uh conclusions that
follow from the information that you've
uh that you've represented. Uh and
that's the basis for reasoning
uh and ultimately for decision-m and
pretty much everything else that goes
on. Um so AI has studied this uh since
the late 1950s, but philosophers have
studied it uh at least for 2500 years uh
almost all under the heading of logic.
So logic is uh dealing with definite
information. Uh probability theory deals
with uncertain information. Um so in
some sense we're starting halfway
through the story, right? We're skipping
over logic. Um if you want you can go
back and read about logic in the
relevant chapters of the textbook. I
think chapter 7, 8, 9, 10, 11 maybe.
Yeah, I think those are the ones. Um
but we'll start with probability and
that actually dovetales with what you've
just covered uh in markoff decision
processes uh except now for example if I
wanted to create a representation
of a large and complex markoff decision
process right in something other than
C++ right you can always use C++ for
everything right because it's a
universal language it's Turing
equivalent right but It's incredibly
inelegu inelegant and uh errorprone to
try to build representations of complex
systems in C++.
And so uh you know ma mathematicians
like to build representations of complex
systems as partial differential
equations not as C++.
they then implement, you know, a
simulator for the PTE in C++ and then
they make mistakes and then they get
errors and and all the rest. But PTEEs
are their formal representation of the
dynamics of a complex system. Uh and for
Markov decision processes, you can use
probability invasion networks uh and
various extensions to represent uh
complex markoff decision processes
elegantly. Okay.
So,
so uncertainty is um is ubiquitous,
right? We
uh you know, we saw it in the the MDP
version of uh of Pac-Man and so on where
um you know, if you remember the little
4x3 world where uh if you move forward,
you might get stuck or you might go off
to the wrong side. So that's sort of an
artificial introduction of stochasticity
into the dynamics of that world. But the
real world, it's the rule, right? And
things like chess and tic-tac-toe and so
on are the exception. And you can think
of determinism is just a special case of
uncertainty where all the uncertainty is
squeezed down to nothing.
Oops. Um,
and so, you know, here's here's a
problem. I typically face, right? I need
to get on a plane and uh it's going from
SFO and I live in Berkeley. Uh you know,
if I leave 90 minutes in advance of the
flight departure time, am I going to get
there on time and be able to board my
flight? Right?
So,
I imagine most of you I actually changed
this from 60 minutes because I just
found it too stressful to even think
about leaving 60 minutes before before
the flight. Um, okay. So, what are the
reasons why you're uncertain about this
question? Right. Yeah.
>> Due to traffic in the first place.
>> Uh, sorry. You said 40 minutes
>> just to reach the airport. Is it exactly
40 minutes?
>> 35 to 45.
>> Is it exactly? So, it's could never be
less than 35 and could never be more
than 45.
>> It depends on your traffic. If it's a
holiday like close to December, then
it's even more.
>> Yeah. It's uh you know, if there's a
bowl game um
and so on, right? So, there are many
many reasons why uh the traffic might be
a long time, right? Um,
now if you could
observe
the current location of every vehicle
and you could look inside the mind of
every driver and find out where they
were going to go and how attentive they
are so they don't rear end someone by
accident and cause a big backup on the
bridge and blah blah blah, right? So
there's tons of stuff that we don't even
observe at all about the state of the
world. And so if you don't even know
what state you're in, then even if you
do know the dynamics perfectly, right?
Even if you've got the perfect partial
differential equation for the universe,
right? If you don't know the state, then
you can't predict the outcome. Um, so
there's stuff you just can't observe at
all, right? You know, for each driver,
where are they going? Have the faintest
idea, right? And then the stuff you do
observe is uh is noisy, right? So, you
might tune to the the traffic station on
AM radio, uh, and it's saying, "Oh,
yeah, there's a slowdown. There's a
stalled vehicle in the right lane on the
Bay Bridge, you know, and then you're on
the Bay Bridge and there's no stalled
vehicle at all, right? So, it's, you
know, it's out of date or it was
misreported or whatever. So, there's
noise in the sensory information that
you do have. And then if you if you knew
all of that, right? So if you had
perfect sensing and you had perfect PTE
model of the universe
right then there's also this problem
that actually computing
the consequences of that information
right so even if you had enough so that
there is a deterministically
well-defined
prediction right actually computing that
prediction would be completely
infeasible right it would mean modeling
you know think about all the tires has
on all the cars that might have a flat
at any moment, right? So, you got to
model all the rubber molecules and all
the nails on the road and everything,
right? It's just vast, incredibly
complex model and we can't possibly do
that. I mean, um, you know, just
modeling one tire for, you know, a 100
miles of rotation, uh, you know, at a
molecular level would probably require
all the supercomputing on Earth, uh, to
do it in real time. So uh so there's the
complexity problem. All right. And then
as we mentioned, right, there's there's
just stuff we don't know, uh about the
dynamics of the world as well,
right? So all that leaves you with these
two sources, right? One is ignorance and
one is laziness. Okay? Okay. And I put
laziness in quotes because it's not, you
know, it's not computationally
uh reasonable to even try to do that
that level of very detailed prediction.
But but it is important to understand
that both of these factors are at play.
Uh and they operate in different ways,
right? So laziness you can fix by not
being lazy, right? By doing more
compute, uh by being more explicit about
your knowledge and writing it all down
in detail and so on. Um, ignorance you
can only fix by changing your access to
the world, right? Actually adding more
sensors or uh doing a bunch of
experiments to find out how quickly
rubber decomposes and all the other
kinds of stuff.
Okay. Um, so you're going to have
uncertainty and we represent that uh
with probabilities. So given you know
given everything that I'm I'm uh I'm I'm
willing to model and willing to reason
about given my laziness uh and given the
limitations on the information I might
say okay there's a you know 55% chance
you know if it's it's a weekday not in
the rush hour um you know it's a it's 11
o'clock in the morning I think it's
about a 55% console be able to get there
and then get to the gate in time uh and
so on so forth.
So you got the probabilities and then as
we saw with markoff decision processes
you will take the probabilities and
combine them with utilities and in
utilities uh in markoff decision process
utilities are just a sum of rewards
but that's a particular
special case. Uh not all utility
functions have to be a sum of rewards.
Uh in fact there's good reason to think
that humans don't actually uh decompose
utilities additively across time in that
way. Um and so
so then your optimal action is the one
that maximizes so the arg over the
actions. Uh and this is the expected
utility. S is the outcome state. So
you're going to take some action that'll
produce a state. And then the utility is
a number associated with a state that
describes uh how good that state is. And
we'll see more about utility theory uh
later on in the class and it's a whole
extremely interesting subject in its own
right. But for now we'll just take that
as a given and we'll focus on the
probability side. So any questions about
this before we go on?
Great. Okay.
Right. So this uh the basic mathematics
of probability you should have had in
CS70.
Uh so this will be review and I'll go
through it fairly quickly. All right. So
the the the first concept in probability
theory is to set up what are the
possible things that could happen,
right? And we'll call those uh possible
worlds. And capital omega is the set of
possible worlds. So, for example, if I'm
going to roll one dice,
then it could come out one, two, three,
four, five, and six. And so, those are
the six possible worlds. We'll ignore
the one where it balances on the corner
and doesn't fall over, right? We'll
assume that that doesn't happen. Um,
and so, uh, so that set of possible
worlds is what we're going to say. We're
going to put probabilities on those and
then that allows us to then do
probabilistic reasoning.
So those are our possible worlds. So a
probability model is a set of possible
worlds with probabilities attached to
each possible world. And so so here
we're just going to put one sixth on
each of the possible worlds.
And so uh that's a very simple
probability model, right? The
probability models that we'll deal with
have millions, billions, quintilions of
possible worlds, sometimes even
infinitely many possible worlds. Uh and
so we need to develop methods of
representing the probability model
without you know writing a number next
to each possible world. Right? So there
that's what we're going to talk about
this week.
And so uh the the laws of probability
are very very simple.
the those numbers that you attach to
each possible world have to be between
zero and one and they have to add up to
one across all the possible worlds.
Right? So that those are the the two
basic laws and then
uh we talk about
uh an event is any subset of those
possible worlds, right? So you could
have the event we could call it in
English that the dice roll is less than
four. uh and that will be equivalent to
just the set one two three. The role is
odd would be the set 135.
Okay. So event is any subset of possible
worlds and the probability
of an event is the sum of the
probabilities of the worlds that are in
the event. Okay. So that's it. Now you
know the laws of probability and these
here I'm doing it with sums and so
that's makes sense for discrete set of
possible worlds or a countable set. If
you're talking about real numbers, if we
are taking a stat class, then they want
to do normal distributions and all stuff
with real numbers, then you it's a bit
more complicated. Uh because there's
there's different ways of dividing up
the real line and that get make a mess
of these very simple concepts. Um but
with discrete possible worlds, it's all
very easy. Okay. So if oops so if a is
an event then you take the possible
worlds that are in the event you sum up
the probabilities of those possible
worlds. So um since ro less than four is
the set one two three then the
probability that the role is less than
four is the sum of those three worlds
and that's equal to a half. Okay it's
all very easy.
Um,
now there's good reasons why these laws
of probability make sense.
Okay? And there have been over the last
couple hundred years many many proposals
for how one could reason with uncertain
information.
Not all of them consistent with the laws
of probability.
And uh so Dave Fenetti showed in 1931
and various other philosophers have done
similar things that um if you make bets
according to any according to degrees of
belief that don't satisfy the laws of
probability
then we can arrange things so that uh
you are guaranteed to lose money on your
bets no matter what happens. So no no
matter which horse wins the race uh if
you bet in violation of the laws of
probability uh you are guaranteed to
lose money. So this is one of the uh the
most fundamental reasons why probability
theory is the right theory for uncertain
reasoning.
Um and it's an example of something more
general which is rationality
constraints. And when we start talking
about utility theory, you'll see that
rationality constraints are uh the basis
for why we want to maximize expected
utility because
any violation of that principle uh leads
to an entity that is can be guaranteed
to lose money. Uh basically you
construct what we call money pumps where
the entity makes a decision uh and hands
over money to you as a result because
they are they're constantly making
decisions that violate the principles of
rationality. Uh and so uh we uh over the
last 250 years or so uh we've generally
come to accept that if you want to talk
about rational decision-m you're talking
about maximization of expected utility.
Okay. Um, so the next concept in
probability theory is that of a random
variable.
Um, and as my my late friend Joe
Halpern, who is a one of the most famous
probabilists in the AI community and
just died a couple of weeks ago, but he
always says, you know, random variables
are neither random nor variables, right?
They're actually deterministic
functions.
Okay, so what does that mean?
Um so when you think about a possible
world right the a dice roll for example
so let's say the dice roll four uh there
are various things you can ask about
that you know is it even is it bigger
than two right and those questions that
you can ask about a possible world are
what we call random variables right and
they have answers uh for each different
world they might have different answers
so it's a deterministic function of a
possible Well, omega.
For example,
um you could have a random variable odd.
Okay, and odd of one is equal to true
and odd of six is equal to false. Okay,
so odd is a random variable. It has a it
has a range. So for odd, it's true
false. Um for uh temperature, it would
be hot and cold. For uh d is duration,
right? that might be any any real number
between zero and and infinity. Um if
you're looking for ghosts in the grid,
then it might the location of the ghost
could be uh any one of a discrete set of
coordinates. So the range is what are
the possible values of this uh random
variable across all the different
possible worlds. And so it's a function
of a possible world. Okay? And that's
that's very helpful to remember that uh
if you ever get confused about what's
going on. So then a probability
distribution
for a random variable
is the probability for each possible
value that it might take on. So each for
each x uh in the range of that uh what
is the probability that the variable and
we always use capital letters variables
takes on the value. We always use
lowercase for value. Uh so that big x
equals little x
and um I'll give you an example in a
second, right? So the probability that
it takes on that value, right? Is that's
because that's an event, right? The the
event that big x takes on value little x
is some set of possible worlds. All the
possible worlds where it has that value.
And so the probability is then the sum
of those worlds, right? the sum of all
the worlds where x of omega equals x uh
times of the sorry summing up the
probabilities of those worlds. Okay. Um
and notationally we can collapse this
expression down to this one when it's
obvious that we're talking about the
variable capital x. Um and then we might
use this p of capital x that refers to
the whole distribution. Right? So p of
little x is some number. So it's a
scalar like 0.2. Uh p of capital x
refers to the uh if you like the vector
of all the probabilities for all the
values of the random variable.
Okay. Uh so I'll introduce the running
example for the rest of lecture uh where
we have um temperature like is it going
to be hot or cold uh and then weather is
it going to be um sunny, rainy, foggy or
meteors.
And um so here are the probability
distributions right you can see it's
like sort of like a vector for hot and
cold 0.5
and the weather is a four element vector
6.1.3 and zero.
Okay.
Um just a note about zero.
Saying that something has probability
zero is equivalent to asserting that
it's logically impossible.
Right? In other words, you would be
willing to bet any amount of money, even
your life, at any odds,
uh, on it not happening. Okay? So, don't
do that, right? Don't do that unless it
really is logically impossible, right?
really logically impossible that you
know x= 2 and x= 3 at the same time
right that can't happen right but
anything that's logically possible you
know has some nonzero probability of
occurring at less so uh you should avoid
using real zeros and real ones uh unless
it's logically certain
okay
um all right Clear? Good. Okay. And then
um the thing we'll be working with most
is called the joint distribution.
And
uh the joint distribution gives you the
value the probability for combinations
of values of the variables. So the joint
distribution over temperature and
weather, right? You got weather here and
temperature there. And then so this
number here says the probability of sun
and cold. So a cold day when it's sunny
uh that occurs 15% of the time.
Okay. So that's a joint distribution. Uh
and again these have to add up to one
because these are since um each of those
is uh these are all disjoint and they
collectively exhaust all possibilities
um and so they would have to add up to
one. Okay.
All clear. Good. All right. Um
okay so if you start from
this notion that okay a probability
model is a set of possible worlds and
then probabilities attached to each
possible world right you're sort of
taking the set of possible worlds as a
as just a given right um and then the
random variables are things that you
apply to a possible world to get a value
right so you take the dice 1 2 3 4 5 six
odd. You apply it to a dice roll and it
says yes or no that's odd or even. Um
but in reality, right, we don't just
start, you know, someone doesn't just
hand us a set of possible worlds. We
have to decide what they are, right? We
have to decide, you know, what do what
are we actually talking about? Uh, you
know, in our little small world that
we're going to construct to reason
about, right? We're not typically we're
not talking about the whole universe,
right? And all the possible ways the
universe could be and all the possible
ways it could be for the rest of time,
right? We're typically talking about
something much smaller like can I get to
the airport? Uh and so I have to build
those possible worlds. I have to decide
really I start actually with the random
variables.
uh and then then I build the possible
worlds out of those.
Um and so uh basically the set of
possible worlds is then the cartesian
product of the ranges of the random
variables that I want to consider in my
problem. All right. So if I'm going to
roll two dice, roll one and roll two.
Okay,
then what what are the possible worlds
that I could get? How many are there?
Yes. 36. Thank you. Okay. Don't be shy.
Right. I can ask you really dumb
questions and you can still answer them.
It's okay. All right. 36.
Right. And that's six times six.
Okay. Uh, so you might ask, well, okay,
but you know, when I'm playing Monopoly
or Craps or any of these games, right,
it doesn't matter whether it's a six and
a four or a four and a six, right? So
those are those are equivalent.
So how would I get that? Well, I could
define a a random variable on top of the
possible world, right? Which is which
would then basically just sort the uh
the two dice rolls. And so if I if I
rolled a four with dice one and a six
with dice two, then sorting that would
give me six and four, right? So high is
first and and that will then become
canonical, right? But the probability of
then getting a six and four would be the
sum of the two worlds
where I would get a six and a four in
the sorted version, namely six and four
and four and six. So, so the sorted roll
or the what we might think of as the
canonical dice roll representation would
have a different probability
distribution from the this sort of raw
random variable assignment.
Okay. Uh so what are their probabilities
for each of those possible worlds?
>> Yep.
>> 36.
>> One over 36. Yep.
Right. because we're assuming for the
sake of argument that the uh each dice
roll is independent
and so uh so the probability of getting
a four and a two is just the product of
the four and the two which is always one
over 36 right um you know if
you're worried that your dice might be
biased
then you can add in a bias variable for
for dice one another biased variable for
dice two. Uh perhaps they're both from
the same manufacturer, in which case the
bias for one and the bias for two might
be correlated with each other and then
the individual dice rolls wouldn't be
independent. You can model all that
stuff and we'll see using basets. It's
very very easy to to build more and more
complex and elaborate models. Uh and
it's sort of it's very very
straightforward.
Okay. Um okay. So here's a very
important thing to remember, right? And
you've you've seen this I think if if
you've been doing any midterm questions
uh for 188 right you you've seen this
over and over again right so if I have n
variables and each of them has a range
size d so they they can take on d
possible values right then what is the
total number of possible worlds that I
can con construct
Well, yeah.
Would it be n times d? No, it would be
more than that.
So, think about for the two dice rolls,
right? So I've got two variables
and each of them has domain size
six
D. Yeah. Um and so the way to think
about that is you know think about this
as an ndigit number
right so this is n the number of digits
in my number right and then d is the the
sort of the base or the radex of each
digit right so if the d was 10 and you
got a six-digit number then it's 10 to
the^ of six right so each of the think
of those you know the slot where you can
put in the value of variable one.
Another slot put in the value of
variable two. So it's always
e to the^ of n.
Okay, it is not n to the power of d.
And I predict about 8% of you will make
that mistake in the midterm even after
I've told you.
Uh but try I mean may just surprise me
for once and let everyone get it right.
That would be great. Um
and so okay so that's that's the obvious
right problem that's going to be hitting
us in the face all the time is that the
uh as you add more variables so as n
increases
uh your the size of your probability
model is growing exponentially
okay uh and if d is infinity right if
it's if these are continuous variables
then it's even worse than that, right?
How do you even begin to represent a
probability distribution
uh over infinitely many possible worlds?
So, probability theorists are very
clever and they've come up with ways to
do that. Um
and uh maybe we'll we'll see some of
those ways later on, but for now we'll
think we'll assume everything is finite.
Um but still exponentially large is is a
big problem. And so basets are really
the best solution we have for making
that uh for beating that exponential
down into something that's much closer
to being linear in the number of
variables.
Okay. Um all right. So let's go through
a few examples. Right. So here here's a
joint distribution over weather and
temperature. And um
uh given that joint distribution uh I
can you know using the standard
definition that the probability of event
is the sum of worlds uh uh in which the
event holds right so I can answer any
question right so what's the probability
that it's hot and sunny
y
Yeah. 045. So, there's only one world
where it's hot and sunny, and that's
that one. So, that was easy. All right.
Good. Good for putting your hand up
first because you got to do the easy
one. Uh, okay. What's the probability
that it's hot?
>> Yes.
>> Uh, yep. That's uh these are all the
worlds where it's hot and you add up the
probabilities, you get 0.5. Good. Okay.
What's the probability that it's hot or
not foggy?
Right. So, which it's maybe a little
easier to say, well, in which world
would this be false?
Well, for it to be false, it has to be
cold and foggy,
right? So the probability that's hot or
not foggy
is all the worlds other than the cold
foggy world, right? And cold foggy world
is this one,
right? And so these are the these are
the worlds,
right? So everything else. So if you add
those up, it's going to be
73.
Okay.
All right. So, so now we can answer uh
arbitrary logical combinations of of
events. So, we have a kind of you know
if you've ever used databases is like
SQL, right? And so now we have a kind of
way of answering queries expressed
against a probability model. We can we
can tell you the probability from this
joint distribution tell you the
probability of of any logical expression
uh in terms of the variables.
Okay. Uh it's so a bit more terminology.
So marginal distributions are lower
dimensional distributions derived from a
higher dimensional distribution. Okay.
And they're called marginal um because
uh a lot of um probability theory was
worked out uh in actuarial business
which is basically life insurance and
things like that. And they used to
collect lots of data and put them in
tables and then they would along the
margins the right margin and the bottom
margin they would add up the rows add up
the columns uh and so on and so that's
why it's called marginal probabilities
because there were probabilities written
in the margin of the page.
Okay. So um so the basic equation right
so if you want if you have a a variable
that you're interested in and you're
coming from a joint distribution with
some other variables you basically just
sum across the values of the other
variables. So we did that uh on the
previous right. So uh we wanted to look
at the probability of hot. So we summed
over the weather values. We got rid of
weather by summing out across the values
of weather. So uh so that's what that
says. And so if I want the marginalss
for weather and temperature, I just
either sum across or I sum down. uh and
that gives me the probability for
temperature 0.5 just the sum of the
columns and the probability for weather
summing across the rows.
Okay. So uh
so this this process marginalization is
one of the standard algebraic operations
that we do uh to get the probabilities
we want from the probabilities that we
have whatever we start with. Um, and you
should think of this as very similar to,
you know, in grade school when you had
um, you know, when you had an uh, an
equation like u equals v + 2 and they
said find v, right? Then you had to
subtract two from both sides and you
said, okay, u minus uh, sorry, u - 2 = v
+ 2 - 2 = v. And now you've got v in
terms of u - 2. So, so you learned all
those algebraic operations to manipulate
uh algebraic equations. Now you just
have to learn a few new operations to
man manipulate expressions involving
probabilities and marginalization is one
of those. Uh and there are a few more.
Okay. All right. Um
so that was marginal probabilities. Now
conditional probabilities and again you
will have seen this in CS70. Um
so uh one way of thinking about
conditional probabilities is just uh a
definition. So the probability of uh of
a given b is the joint probability for a
and b divided by the probability for b.
So remember the thing on the right goes
on the bottom. Okay? And um and you the
way I think the right way to think about
it is to say okay if I'm if I have um
if I have a universe of possibilities
right so so for a these are all the
worlds where A is true these are all the
worlds where B is true the intersection
are the worlds where both A and B are
true
right so if I this is called
conditioning on B right so given that
I've observed B to be true. What is now
my belief about A? Right? That's the
right that's the way to think about a
conditional probability. Well, given
that I observe B is true means just look
in the worlds where B is true. So
completely ignore all the ones where B
is false and just look at this becomes
your universe, right? And then the ones
where A is true is the intersection. So
the probability of A given B is like how
much mass is in the intersection out of
the mass that's in uh the B worlds.
Okay. And so those are the B worlds and
then this is the mass that's in the
intersection. So you just take that
fraction. Okay.
So if I if again I have my joint
distribution I want to compute uh the
probability that the weather is sunny
given that the temperature is cold.
Okay. So I restrict myself to the world
the worlds where it's cold. So I look at
these ones. Okay. And now what fraction
of those? So the total mass there is 15
and 8 is 23 and 27 is 0.5.
Okay. And so I've got a uh for the sunny
case I've got 0.15 out of five.
Right? And so that's equal to 0.15
divided by five is.3. So I can basically
uh just
focus on the parts of the universe that
already agree with the thing I'm
conditioning on the thing I've observed
and then within that universe I'm just
looking at okay what fraction of
probability mass has is the thing I care
about.
Any questions?
Okay.
Um okay. So we can extend that concept
the conditional probability of of one uh
event giving another to actually have
conditional distributions. So uh the
conditional distribution meaning the
probability for all possible values of a
variable given some observations.
Okay. So we might want to know what's
the probability distribution for the
weather given that we know the
temperature is hot.
Okay. So we restrict ourselves to hot.
So we're in that column.
And then uh we can look at okay the
total mass is total mass of this is 0.5.
So 045 over 5 is 0.9. 002 over.5 is 04
and so on. Okay. So this is the
conditional distribution for weather
given that the temperature is hot.
Okay. Um this is the one for uh weather
given the temperature is cold. Uh I can
even put those together and get the
conditional conditional distribution for
the weather variable given the
temperature variable. Okay. And this is
not the same as a joint distribution.
Right? Think of so joint distribution
think of as a uh basically a
highdimensional matrix. If I've got here
I have two variables. So it's a a
regular two-dimensional matrix. If I had
three variables, it's a
three-dimensional matrix. And all axes
of that of that matrix are are
equivalent, right? There there's there's
no priority in the axis. Whereas for a
conditional distribution like this one,
okay, I should think of this as for each
value of the temperature, I have a
distribution for the weather. And so
it's this is a vector of vectors rather
than a 2x4 rather than a two dimensional
matrix. Okay. Um
all right.
So here's another standard operation um
normalizing a distribution
right which means to restore the the
property of being a uh a natural
distribution right which is that the
entries have to sum to one
uh and it's a very straightforward I
mean it's exactly what you think if if
they if they don't add up to one I scale
them by the appropriate amount so that
they do add up to one and the amount you
have to scale them by is the sum of the
entries that you that you start with and
then uh divide by that. So we'll see in
the in the book we use um alpha to mean
one over the sum of all the entries.
And so if I look at um the probability
distribution for weather uh given cold
okay then it's this unnormalized
distribution right it adds up to 0.5
instead of one okay so that means that
alpha equals 1 /.5
so alpha equals 2 and so I just scale
all the numbers by by two so norm
normalizing then restores that to be a
normalized distribution by multiplying
by two and magically it now adds up to
one. Okay, so it's this is all very
trivial but it's useful to have these
concepts
as sort of unitary operations, right?
Just like you know moving the two to the
other side you just do it uh you know
automatically you just you just you're
uh you're now good at algebra so you
need to become good at manipulating
these probability expressions.
Okay. uh another law of probability
that's derived from uh from the basic
laws in fact from the here from the
definition of conditional probability
right
um
and uh so the product rule does that and
it says that the pro is basically right
we take the definition of conditional
probability we multiply by p of b so p
of a given b time p of b is equal to p
of a and b Okay,
so that's the
that's the product rule and and
notice what happens here, right? So
typically in expressions involving
probabilities,
there's the stuff on the right hand side
of the conditioning bar and the stuff on
the left hand side of conditioning bar.
In fact, you can think of PB as as P of
B given nothing, right? So
without any information, my prior belief
about B is P of B. So think of that as
nothing. And so you'll often find these
probabilities in pairs, right? There'll
be a an expression where B is on the
right and another expression where B is
on the left. Okay? And if you find in
the middle of your uh homework that I've
got two two probability
uh things and B is on the left in both
of them, right? then you're like, have I
gone wrong somewhere? Did I forget to
flip or did I use baze rule or product
rule in the wrong way? Uh it doesn't
always come out that way, but it's a
good good rule of thumb to remember that
they they will typically go in pairs.
Okay, so that's the product rule. Um you
know, I'm not going to go through the
example as it's too obvious, right? Just
then the um the generalization of the
product rule is called the chain rule,
right? And you can take a joint
distribution on on some number of
variables, right? You can apply the
product rule first to the last variable.
So that's equal to P of X3,
right? So here you're treating X1 and X2
as if they were a single variable,
right?
uh and then you can break down P of X1
X2 using the product rule again. So now
you get that. Okay. So now you've taken
a joint distribution over three
variables and you've got the product of
three conditional distributions each of
which has only one variable on the left
of the conditioning bar.
Okay. Um and in general right that works
for any number of variables. You can
just repeat the process. Uh and so you
will see this kind of expression over
and over again. Uh it's the product over
all the variables of the probability of
the variable conditioned on all the
preceding variables in the sequence.
Okay. And you can see that happening in
in this case up here with the three
variables. Right? So the chain rule
turns out to be uh central to how we
understand basets uh which will be in
the next lecture.
Just want to keep track of my time.
Okay. I think we're good.
All right.
Okay. So now for the for the rest of
today, we're going to do simple-minded
probabilistic inference.
Okay. So this is just working with those
joint distributions, those big tables.
Um,
and we'll see how to answer uh the
questions you want, which is typically
what's the probability of a query
variable. So the thing I care about
given all the things that I've observed.
Okay. Okay. So I if I want to know am I
going to get to the airport on time
then you know I might check the radio
and it says you know everything is
flowing freely no accidents reported.
Okay. And um and so I might have you
know I I do my calculations in my giant
probability model and I compute 0.9 I'm
going to get there on time. Okay. Um
it's important to understand
that uh when the evidence changes
your belief in the proposition that you
care about the query is also going to
change right and it doesn't mean that
the previous belief was wrong it's just
a different belief right one is a belief
when I've just observed no accidents the
other is a belief when I observe no
accidents and I check the clock and it
says is 5 a.m. Right? So now I know what
time it is and that changes my belief,
right? It's 5:00 a.m. So traffic
probably hasn't started. So it's more
likely I'll get there on time. Okay? Uh
but then if I find out that it's
raining,
then my probability might go down. So
all these three probabilities, they're
all consistent with each other, right?
They're not disagreeing. They're just
statements about uh different
circumstances
uh epistemic circumstances, right? What
you know uh in terms of your evidence uh
different epistemic circumstances you
can be in.
Okay. Um
so the the general way we're going to do
this uh is to start from our giant joint
distribution
and we'll you know so the in general
right there will be n variables x1
through xn and so it's a big n-
dimensional table
and um we want to know the probability
for the query variables in the examples
I just gave that's am I going to get to
the airport on time. Um, I'll have some
observed evidence. So, the variables E
will have value little E, right? And
that could be uh several of those.
Several of those evidence variables
might be what time is it? What's the
weather? What's the traffic report?
Maybe is there a ball game? Uh maybe,
you know, do I have a flat tire? Right?
There's a a number of things you could
observe that would be the evidence.
And then all the other variables which
are neither query nor evidence, we'll
call those the hidden variables.
Okay.
And so the question is can we use the
rules of probability that we learn to
figure out how to answer the question
that we're interested in which is what's
the probability of the query given the
evidence. Right? Assuming that we have
this joint distribution over all the
variables and the answer is yeah it's
not that hard. Right? Right. So we want
the probability for the query variables
given the evidence we've observed.
And uh basically uh you first of all
narrow your joint distribution down to
the parts of the universe consistent
with the evidence you've observed,
right? Um and so that would mean you
know if you observed three evidence
variables and you had a 10-dimensional
table, right? then you're collapsing it
down to a seven-dimensional table
looking just at the parts that are
consistent with the evidence you
observed. Okay? And then
you sum out those variables. So
marginalizing out getting rid of uh the
variables that you don't want. So those
are the hidden variables.
Uh and so if you start with the joint
distribution, so the joint distribution
is the query variables, the hidden
variables, the evidence variables.
Right? We sum out all possible values of
the hidden variables
and that gives us then the joint
distribution over the query and the
evidence. Right? So that's marginalizing
out the hidden variables.
Uh and then we are just going to
normalize that. We're going to turn it
into a conditional distribution um by uh
by multiplying by the normalization
factor.
Okay. So, um All right. So, where is the
hard part in this?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. It's a summing out over H, right?
So,
so typically your query is one or two
variables, your evidence maybe, you
know, four or five variables. And the
hidden variables, there can be loads of
them, right? And so the number of
combinations that you have to sum over
is exponential in the number of hidden
variables.
And so generally if n is large
uh then you're facing an exponentially
large computation
uh to to just to do this, right? But for
now, we're not going to worry about
that. Um we're actually going to do some
okay. So let's say I want uh the
probability distribution for the
weather. Okay.
So given here we're conditioning on no
evidence at all. Right? Then how do we
how do we find that? Right? Well, we um
so first of all we condition on the
evidence. So we collapse down to the
parts where the evidence is is true. But
here there is no evidence. So we stick
with the original joint distribution.
Um, I've added another variable here
just to make it a bit more interesting.
The season, so it could be summer or
winter. And that season changes the
distributions of uh of hot and cold and
sunny and foggy and so on. Okay.
Yeah. Someone who's not someone who's
not sitting at the front. So, we have a
question. Okay. Go ahead.
>> Does the order matter in which we sum up
the hidden variables? Does the order
matter in which we sum out the hidden
variables? Um not not mathematically in
the sense that you can sum them out in
any order and you get the same answer,
right? And that's just because addition
is commutive and associative. Um later
on when we see algorithms for basets uh
which are much more efficient than this
dumb algorithm uh we'll see that it does
matter which which order you sum things
out. Um but yeah, we'll get to that.
Okay.
All right. So, I'll go through this one.
How do we find the distribution for for
the weather? So, let's say I want uh
let's start with um weather equals
sunny, right? So, I'm just going to look
at
uh the the cases where weather is sunny,
right? Sun sun.
Okay. Um
uh and I'm going to add those up, right?
And so 35 point45
6.
Okay. And then weather equals rain.
Uh we get 0.1 2 that's 03.1
and 6. So that's uh 0.1 and so on. Okay.
And so what I'm doing there is I'm
actually summing over the hidden
variables which are the season and the
temperature, right? I'm looking at each
season and temperature uh combination
and uh and then looking at the entry for
weather and then I'm adding those up. So
by adding those up, I'm summing over the
possible values of season and
temperature uh to get the uh the joint
entry for weather.
Okay.
All clear. So now we're going to do um
the probability distribution for the
weather.
>> Yeah.
>> Well, so I I to find this, right? So I
took this entry, this entry, this entry,
and this entry. And so I added those up.
So those four entries
are the ones I obtain by saying okay
summer and hot uh summer and cold winter
and hot uh winter and cold. Okay so I'm
enumerating the possible values of the
hidden variables and then looking up to
see what is the what is the probability
for weather and then adding up those
entries. Okay. So that's what summing
over means is just enumerating the
possible combinations. Yeah. Okay.
Okay.
So now probability for the weather given
that it's winter, right? So so now the
first step becomes non-trivial. I do
have some evidence. So I have to
basically focus in on the universe where
the evidence is true, right? And that
means okay, well it's winter, so we
ignore the summer, right? So just
pretend that doesn't exist, right? Okay.
And then we do the same thing, right?
Except now we only have the one hidden
variable
which is the temperature. So if I want
to know uh if I want to know W equals
uh sunny, right? Then there's that one
and that one.
Okay. So now I'm just enumerating over
one variable, right? Those are two
different values for temperature, hot
and cold.
And um so I add those up. That's uh
that's 0.15,
right? We'll do it again for rain.
So that's 01 and 06. So that's 0.07
and so on. Um in fact, you know what?
I'll finish this and then we'll we'll do
the normalization step as well. Uh so
for fog
that's uh 02 and
18. So that's 0.20.
And for meteor that's always
zero.
So if I add those up to get the
normalization factor that's 22.42.
Right? So the posterior distribution so
then the probability for weather given
winter
is 1 over.42*
42 times.1
oops.15
uh 07.20
and then 0 0. Okay. So I I'm not going
to do the arithmetic in my head. Um but
that gives that then gives you the
posterior distribution uh meaning poster
post posterior meaning distribution
after conditioning on the evidence
for uh the weather given that it's
winter.
Okay.
All right. So as I said this is the big
problem right in general the number of
the queer variables is small. Yeah.
how
>> sorry okay so here I had um the evidence
being that it's winter okay so season
>> so season equals winter right so yeah
the thing I'm conditioning on right
typically that's what you I've observed
that it's winter and now I want to do my
weather forecast okay all Right.
Okay. Um, so in general, right, your
your number of query variables might be
one or maybe a couple. Number of
variables is small. It might be, you
know, a handful, 10, 20. Um, but you
might have a thousand variables in your
model. And so
just doing that process of summing over
all the combinations of hidden variables
uh ends up being uh intractable.
So that's the first problem, right?
The second problem is how on earth would
you store the joint distribution in the
first place? Right? If I have a thousand
variables,
right?
Even if they're just boolean variables,
right? They only have two values. That's
two to the power of a thousand.
That's about 10 to the
10 to the log 10 of two, which is uh
about 300,
right? So 301
um
right which is and how big is the
universe?
How many atoms does the universe have?
About 10 to the 80.
Right?
So this is 10^ the 220 times bigger than
the universe. Even if you could store
each probability on a single atom,
right? we're
we're not even getting started when
we've used up the whole universe. Okay,
so that's another problem. Um,
and then maybe the worst problem is well
where would you get those probabilities
from in the first place, right? If if
you're learning them from data,
right? Which is, you know, the the big
data religion these days, everything has
to be learned from data. Well, you're
trying to learn 10 to the 300 numbers.
So you're probably going to need, you
know, at least 100 times that many to
get reasonably accurate statistics. So
10^ the 302
uh data points, right? So so clearly uh
something isn't working here, right? Um
so it's not it's not really the the time
complexity. It's not really the space
complexity. It's that you couldn't even
build a thing in the first place if this
was how you think about probability
models.
Okay? But notice, right, for the dice
roll case,
right? Did I have to do
so if I have two dice and I roll them
both, right? Do I have to do six times
as many experiments?
And if I had three dice, would I have to
do 30 times 36 times as many
experiments?
If I had 10 dice, would I have to do,
you know, billions times more
experiments to fill in my probability
table? Of course not. Right? Because I
know something about the structure of
this probability model. I know in the
case of the dice that they're
independent and all the dice are
identical and that they're all
symmetrical. And so I know without doing
really doing any experiments that uh
they're all one six one sixth and and
then it's the for any given entry in the
table, it's just the product of all
those one sixth values across all the
dice. So it's one six to the power of
however many dice there are and that's
the number and there you know so I can
fill out that giant table with 10^ the
300 entries um without doing uh any
experiments at all or if I insist I
could roll one of the dice a few times
make sure it really is unbiased and and
fill it in that way.
Okay. Um so we'll see that basets fix
all these problems to a large extent.
um by decomposing that joint
distribution into small pieces each of
which can be estimated separately from
data. Uh and this is in some way this is
the basis for the whole of science,
right? is that our model of the universe
is decomposed into small pieces and each
piece can be estimated separately uh
rather than having to run experiments on
the whole universe uh and record the
results.
Okay, let's see how we're doing on time.
All right, good. Uh okay, so the next
piece of probability math, Baze rule.
Again, you should have seen this in
CS70. And so bas
the most trivially derived, right? So
how could you how could baze be so
famous for doing something so simple,
right? Which is to write the product
rule uh both ways,
right? So p of a equals b sorry p of a
and b is p of a given b p of b. It's
also p of b given a p of a, right? So
this thing is equal to that thing. uh
and then you divide those two by P of B
and you get P of A given B is P of B
given A times P of A divided by P of B.
Okay. So this is B rule and um
there that's my rule. So interestingly
you'll see that you'll see this picture
of you know whenever whenever you look
up Baze you'll see this picture of Mr.
Baze. But in fact, we don't know what
Mr. Bae looked like. U and somehow this
picture got misidentified as as Mr. Ba.
It's just a picture of a generic 17th
century British clergyman. Uh and we
don't know who his name is either. Um
but it got it got somehow attached to
Thomas Bae. Um, so but yeah, you can go
to Thomas Ba's uh cemetery uh sorry, his
his grave in London in the cemetery and
it's it's always covered in flowers
because even 300 and something years
later Basians are still showing up to
put flowers on his grave. So it's very
nice.
Okay, so what is this basal thing,
right? What use is it? Right? It's just
this trivial manipulation of the product
rule. Um but it underlies a whole way of
thinking about everything right basians
know the answer to every question right
you know in statistics there's the
basians and the frequentists and the
basians you know look at the
frequentists struggling with all these
questions about how to estimate things
from the data and they just they sort of
laugh they say oh well you know one day
you'll you'll come to a true basian
belief uh and you'll then you'll you'll
understand that all of those things
you're confused about will just
evaporate,
right? Um, and
the big the big thing about this
equation is, you know, you're starting
from your prior belief in something that
you care about. So, a right. So, a could
be, you know, am I going to get the
airport on time? Uh, you know, do I have
this disease?
uh or even you know what is the correct
physical theory of the universe
right so a could be a hypothesis or one
of many possible hypotheses about the
true laws of physics okay uh and then
you observe some evidence and now you've
got the posterior distribution
so if you're a doctor that's okay I
observe some symptoms now I can get a
more refined notion of whether the
patient has a disease
If you're a scientist, you've done some
observations of the of the heavens or
whatever it might be and now you've got
a more refined belief about what is the
true theory of physics of the universe.
Right? So it covers everything, right?
This is in some sense uh the equation
that describes how one should learn
correctly from experience.
uh whether the experience is the output
of a scientific instrument or the you
know the the voices and noise and
perceptual inputs that a baby gets when
they're born or or the symptoms that a
doctor observes with a patient right and
so you start with this and you multiply
by this thing right P B given A divided
by PB and that gives you the updated uh
belief in the thing you care about
okay so Um,
so that's this
justification, right? It describes an
update step from the prior belief to the
posterior belief when you observe some
evidence.
Um,
another important view is it enables you
to flip that across that conditioning
bar, right? And
so in many cases uh the the information
you know about how the world works is
the probability of effect
given
cause. Right? So that's your causal
theory of the universe. Right? So you
know if you have such and such a disease
then with some probability you know you
will have a rash or you will have a
stiff neck or you will have a fever
right that tells you that's your causal
theory of the universe right if it rains
then the grass will be wet
okay but the reasoning you have to do
often in the real world is that you're
given the effect you observe the
consequences you observe a patient who
has a fever and a rash and doesn't have
a stick neck or you observe that the
grass is wet and then you're trying to
infer this hidden cause which is, you
know, did it rain last night or did my
neighbor put this the sprinkler on? Uh
or did the dog pee on the grass or
whatever it might be? Why the grass is
wet? Um or you know the if you're the
doctor, one of several possible diseases
you're trying to infer from the effects
that you observe. So this is why we
often want to flip this conditioning
because our theories of physics if you
like our causal theory of the world is
in one direction but the question that
you're asked is in the other direction
right you given the observed effects and
you want to figure out the underlying
cause
okay um
think okay we can cover that we have six
minutes wow I cover lots of six
Okay. Um, so now we're going to start on
the things that allow you to
uh to structure probability
distributions in a way that reduces the
uh the size of the representation, the
number of parameters you have to
estimate estimate from data uh and so
on. And the simplest one as I already
described for coin tosses is
independence.
Right? So two variables are absolutely
independent if the joint probability is
the product of the marginal
probabilities.
Okay. Uh and this is the this is the
case for um for coins
where the two dice rolls are assumed not
to uh affect each other. So um you know
an equivalent way of saying it is if I
observe one of the dice rolls y does
that change my belief in what the other
dice roll is going to be right and so
independence says yeah sure if I rolled
a five with one dice it doesn't doesn't
change what the other dice is going to
do it's still going to pick out the six
numbers with equal probability so in
that case we would say the two dice
rolls are independent so you can write
independence
uh either this way or in terms of
conditionals saying that the conditional
probability is unaffected by the
evidence of the other variable.
Okay. Um so as we saw right so for for
dice rolls roll one and roll two right
the probability that you roll a five and
a three is by assumption right because
we're assuming independence the product
of the of the individual roles right so
whether it makes sense to assume
independence
right that's something that you you
bring to the problem right from your
understanding of the causal structure of
the system that's generating um the
observables.
Okay. And for dice rolls,
if you're if you're reasonably sure that
these are not fake magic dice, right?
Then uh it's reasonable to assume that
they're independent.
Okay? But if someone said, "Okay, these
are fake magic dice. I'm not going to
tell you what number they tend to
produce, but I'm just going to tell you
that they're fake magic dice and they
always they're loaded to produce one
number. Right? When I roll the first one
and see that it's a five, that changes
my belief that I'm going to get a five
with the other one. Right? And so makes
it more likely that the other one is a
five if I know that they're both loaded
magic dice made the same way. Okay.
Um so so the nice thing is right
if you have uh if you have n independent
variables for example coin flips, dice
rolls and so on right your joint
distribution would have two to the n
entries.
Okay, but those can be constructed by
multiplying the individual probabilities
for each coin because of independence.
So you might, if you really wanted to
test each of your coins or each of your
dice independently, make sure that
they're biased or unbiased, right? You
can you can get uh you get the n uh
separate coin flip probabilities for
each coin. Once you've got those
probabilities, then it's independent and
uh you can construct the whole table
from a a linear amount of information.
Okay, so that's that's huge, right? That
gives you this exponential reduction
from 2 to the n down to n parameters.
Um,
but it almost never happens.
Okay? And that's that's a bummer.
Okay?
So, and and the reason it almost never
happens is because you know that dice
rolls are somehow right they're
specially designed to be random and
independent. Okay, but uh if you pick
any pair of random variables in the
world,
the chances are that they are not going
to be independent of each other because
you can come up with some causal story
where uh that would create a dependence
between them.
But what we find instead is that
conditional independence uh is almost
ubiquitous. Right? Almost all systems
exhibit a great deal of conditional
independence structure
and uh and so basets are designed to
take advantage of that by representing
the conditional dependencies and
independencies in the domain and those
conditional independencies also reduce
an ex what would be an exponentially
large table down to something that's
roughly linear in the number of
variables. Okay, but it's much much more
common in the real world. So we'll see
examples of that.
So conditional independence um
right is it's like independence except
it's independence conditioned on
observing some variable uh some other
variable that essentially cuts the
dependence between the two things that
you're wondering are these dependent on
each other. Okay, I think I'll skip over
Ghostbusters because it takes a little
bit long to describe and I'll just go to
some other common sense examples.
Excuse me. Deep.
Okay. So the definition of conditional
independence right is that